<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Archidamus, or, The councell of warre Being 2000. yeares old, and written by Isocrates the couragious orator, translated by a Tho: Barnes.</title>
            <title>Archidamus. English</title>
            <author>Isocrates.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1624</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 56 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A04141</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 14280</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S126454</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99856094</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99856094</idno>
            <idno type="VID">21613</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A04141)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 21613)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 991:19)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Archidamus, or, The councell of warre Being 2000. yeares old, and written by Isocrates the couragious orator, translated by a Tho: Barnes.</title>
                  <title>Archidamus. English</title>
                  <author>Isocrates.</author>
                  <author>Barnes, Thomas, Minister of St. Margaret's, New Fish Street, London.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[38] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by William Iones for Nicholas Bourne, and are to be sold at his shop at the south entrie of the Royall Exchange,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1624.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A-E⁴ (-E4).</note>
                  <note>The first leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Variant: title omits all after "councell of warre."; title page a cancel?.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Greece --  History --  Spartan and Theban Supremacies, 404-362 B.C. --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:21613:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21613:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>ARCHIDAMVS, <hi>OR,</hi> THE COVNCELL OF WARRE.</p>
            <p>Being 2000. yeares old, and written by <hi>Iſocrates</hi> the
couragious Orator, tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlated by a <hi>Tho: Barnes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>William Iones</hi> for <hi>Nicholas
Bourne,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop at the South entrie of the
Royall Exchange. 1624.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:21613:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21613:2"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Eing in my apprentiſhip of Grammar Schoole, I caſt a view
vpon that excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent and moſt famous <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>negyrique</hi> Oration, about
which as ſome ſay, that flower of oratorie <hi>Iſocrates</hi> was in
hammering ten yeares or more. But mine eye glauncing a little further, I
chanced to reade that little leſſe admirable Oration to King
<hi>Philip,</hi> which the Grecians ſo reueren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, inaſmuch as King
<hi>Philip</hi> and his ſonne and heire <hi>Alexander</hi> by reading
thereof, were ſtirred vp to ſet vpon the kingdome of <hi>Perſia.</hi> But
proceeding, I hapned vpon this no leſſe famous then the reſt, entituled
<hi>Archidamus;</hi> in the beginning whereof I found ſuch excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie of
elocution, that it ſtill more inflamed the ſcorching heate of my deſire
to reade it more exactly then the othets. Firſt, becauſe it was vndertaken
in ſo important a cauſe, and for ſo <pb facs="tcp:21613:3"/> Potent, and ſo Noble
deſcended a young <hi>Prince:</hi> Secondly, becauſe in this Oration was
required varietie of matter, Monarchicall, Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litarie, publike and priuate,
either aduance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment or ruine; and laſtly becauſe it ſeemes to mee the
Orator ſpent his beſt vigour and ſtrength of wit, and learning at leaſt
to paral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lell, if not to excell his other Orations.</p>
            <p>But the noiſe I now heare of preparation for warre, hath made
theſe his Arguments, and whole diſcourſe not only to run in my minde, but
alſo to run out at my pen. Hath my plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull inſtructor
<hi>Iſocrates</hi> taught me to ſpeake any Greeke? why ſhould not I teach
him to ſpeake a little Engliſh? In attempting where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, I doe but pay a
part of that gratitude, which I owe him as a reward for mine educa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which
kinde of duty he in this Oration calleth by the name of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.
If any man thinke that I ſoare too high in medling with Orations that
concerne politique affaires. I anſwer that in our Schooles we reade all
man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Hiſtories and diſcourſes, wherein we looke after only the
outward barke of the phraſe, and Rhetoricall figures. My end and <pb facs="tcp:21613:3"/>
taske is only a <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, not of ſouldiers, but of words,
conſtruction of Phraſes, not applicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Hiſtories. Therefore (good
Reader) ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept my petty labours, and pardon mine er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours, remembring that thy
ſelfe either art a yong learner, (like my ſelfe) or, hauing beene ſo,
haſt learned at leaſt this leſſon <hi>Minori par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere,</hi> (that is)
not to ſtrike with deeper cenſure thoſe that haue not withdrawne their
hand from the ferula.</p>
            <p>Courtious Reader, farewell, and proſper, which is the word
wherewith now I ſalute <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> Schoole, thence hoyſing
ſayle for <hi>Eton.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thomas Barnes.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="argument">
            <pb facs="tcp:21613:4"/>
            <head>THE ARGVMENT.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Fter the battell at <hi>Leuctra,</hi> the <hi>Thebanes</hi>
inuaded <hi>Lacedemon,</hi> and made much ſpoile of them, ſo as the
Lacedemonians flying and their wiues running to them, thus ſpake, Can we
again receiue you in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to our wombes? Whereupon they char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging the enemy, gaue
them the ouerthrow at Mantinea, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſtoutly aided by a troupe of the
Athenian horſemen. After this ouerthrow at <hi>Mantinea,</hi> by
Embaſſadours they demanded a league or peace of the <hi>Thebanes:</hi> who
promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed it vpon this condition, that they ſhould reedifie
<hi>Meſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na,</hi> and ſuffer it to be a free Citie: which ſome
counſelled the Lacedemonians to yeeld vnto, but <hi>Archidamus</hi> the
younger aduiſed them to the contrary. This Prince <hi>Archi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damus</hi> was
ſonne to King <hi>Ageſilaus.</hi> Some ſay, that <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chidamus</hi>
ſending to <hi>Athens,</hi> obtained this Oration from <hi>Iſocrates,</hi>
others ſay, that <hi>Iſocrates</hi> penned it to exerciſe his Oratorie,
and to ſhew what might be ſpoken by <hi>Archida<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus,</hi> aduiſing the
<hi>Lacedemonians</hi> in their Senate, or Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament. And this is the
Argument: the kinde of this Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is deliberatiue, the principall matter is
profit, or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pediencie.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:21613:4"/>
            <head>ARCHIDAMVS, OR, THE COVNCELL OF WARRE.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ome of you peraduenture won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, that I who haue hitherto kept
the Lawes of our Citie, ſo as I know not whither any of my equalls haue done,
ſhould haue ſo changed my maner, that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning thoſe things which mine
Elders would feare to ſpeake of, I who am yet but of blooming yeares ſhould
begin to deliuer my opinion: but if any of them who are wont to make
deliberatiue orations among you, had ſpoken as the dignitie and the honour of
the Cittie required, I had been ſilent; But perceiuing of them to whom the
<hi>Commaunders in warre</hi> commit the authoritie, or precedency, not
ſtoutly to oppoſe, and others to be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together mute. I aroſe vp, that I
might declare what I thought concerning theſe affaires. For if I ſhould
keepe a retired ſtate of life, I ſhould hold it a ſhame for to vſe the
matter, that the Cittie ſhould haue a reſpect to the ſafety, and not to
the honour thereof. And I ſuppoſe that if in any it be lawfull for young
men to <pb facs="tcp:21613:5"/> giue their opinions, then in this ſurely: to perſwade
to warre or peace is moſt fit for them on whom the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt part of the
danger ſhall redound; and then eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially when it concerneth all in
generall to ſee, and to vnderſtand what is fit to be done. For if it
ſhould ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare that they who are graue, and ſtricken in yeares, onely
concerning all things iudge rightly, and that young men ſhould be in all
things deceiued: then they might take iuſtly from vs this priuiledge of
deliuering our opinions in conſultation; but ſith it conſiſteth not in
multitude of yeares, that we ſhould excell on ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in wiſedome, but in
the induements of nature, and diligence of cricumſpection, or care, why
ſhould wee not (both of young and old) make tryall of the moſt able, that
of ſuch things as ſhall be conſulted of, yee may take the moſt
expedient? it is wonderfull to me that you ſhould ſo abſurdly thinke,
that we whom yee allow worthie to commaund both at ſea and land, whereby we
cannot miſcarry without great hurt to our Cittie, ſhould not open our
mouthes to conſult of thoſe things of which you of your ſole power are to
determine: wherein if we rightly iudge, all receiue a common benifit: and if we
misiudge, the diſhonour is onely ours, without any hurt or impeachment to the
publique.</p>
            <p>Nor hath any deſire of ſpeaking, or changing my former
courſe of life, begot in me this opinion concerning theſe affaires: but
that I would exhort you not to oppoſe the incitments of ſuch as are not
elder then my ſelfe, but out of age to ſeek out who are able to giue
touching the preſent eſtate of things ſome good and profitable aduiſe.
For neuer ſince this was <pb facs="tcp:21613:5"/> made a State, did either warr or danger
offer ſo waigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie a conſideration, as the things now to be deliberated of.
In former times we ſtroue for dominion with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, but now not to put our
ſelues vnder our ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies deſignes or demaunds: which is an argument of
libertie: in defence whereof no perills are to be refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, not of vs onely,
but of all others who would keepe the reputation of manhood, and diſpiſe
not the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation of vertue. And for mine owne part, (if I may ſpeake
what concerneth mine owne particular) I had rather dig and looſe my life for
refuſing to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go the conditions of the imperious demaunds of mine
enemies, then to prolong my dayes much beyond the ordinarie courſe of nature,
by yeelding to the Treatie of the <hi>Thebans:</hi> For it were a ſhamefull
diſhonour for me deſcended from <hi>Hercules,</hi> and from a Father which
ſwayeth the Scepter of a Kingdome, who am alſo Heire apparant of the ſame
State of honour, to giue way as much as in me lieth, that the State which our
Anceſtours left vs, ſhould come to the managing of thoſe who haue beene
vnder our ſeruice and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iection; wherein I would haue you to conſent
with me, well knowing that in the <hi>Theban</hi> warre, though fortune haue
not fauoured vs, and through our Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines miſleading errours, we haue not
in our bodies been conquerours, yet did euer cary the mindes of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uincible
conquerours.</p>
            <p>And if for feare of any imminent dangers we depart from our owne
right, we ſhall ſtrengthen the inſolency of the <hi>Thebans,</hi> and
ſhall erect the Trophe againſt vs more conſpicuous, and illuſtrious
then that of <hi>Leuctra:</hi> for that was done by much fortune; but this by
our <pb facs="tcp:21613:6"/> owne choiſe and voluntary pulling of miſchiefe vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
vs.</p>
            <p>Let me therefore perſwade you not with ſo great diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honor to
blemiſh this Citty, for our aſſociates haue to vnaduiſedly giuen
councell that we ſhould entertaine peace, (<hi>Meſſena</hi> being left
out) with which our aſſoci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ates you ſhould be iuſtly much more
offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with thoſe who from the beginning haue defected and fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len
away from you: for they when they had alienated themſelues from our
friendſhip, haue ouerthrowne their owne Citties with ſeditions and
ſlaughters, the whole State declining into worſe. But theſe doe
pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to vndoe you, who doubt not but to perſwade you to caſt away in
a ſmall moment all the glory which our Progenitours with many dangers, within
the ſpace of 700 yeare haue purchaſed and eſtated vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on vs. Then which
the <hi>Lacedemonians</hi> could inuent nothing more grieuous, nothing more
contumelious: ſo that furthermore, they are ſo deſirous to ſatisfie
themſelues with our dammage, and ſuppoſe vs to be ſo addicted to
cowardiſe: that they which thinke it honorable that yee ſhould often
vndertake warre for your owne eſtates, iudge it not meete that ye ſhould
vndergoe any perill in the behalfe of <hi>Meſſena.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And that they may the better enioy their owne, they aſſay to
teach you, how it behoueth you to ſubmit to the enemie what is yours; and
further more, doe threaten vs that if wee yeeld not to theſe ill men, they
will make conditions of peace for themſelues a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, without vs: and I thinke
the danger will not be ſo great, the honour will be vnto you without them,
more conſpicuous, illuſtrious, and your name before <pb facs="tcp:21613:6"/> all men
more glorious. And if not by others, but by your owne powers or endeuours you
can ſaue guard, or defend your ſelues, and vanquiſh your enemies: this
ſhalbe very agreable to the other former braue acts of this State. And albeit
I haue not beene an admirer of thoſe men whoſe beſt abilitie is in
oratorie, but rather ſuſpected theſe who are nimble in the tongue; to be
whit-livered in their hands. Yet now I deſired no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more then I might
haue liberty to ſpeake accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to mine owne opinion, of thoſe things
which are now in agitatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, (in performing wherof) I hope I ſhall doe good
ſeruice to the common wealth at this time.</p>
            <p>And firſt of all it behoueth you to remember in what manner you
got the Cittie of <hi>Meſsena;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Now called
Morea.</note> and for what cauſes ye were firſt planted or ſeated in
<hi>Pelopome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus,</hi> being at the firſt <hi>Doreans;</hi> and therefore I
will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin to repeate the matter a little farther off, that ye may
vnderſtand that Prouince to be taken from you, which yee poſſeſſe by
as good right as all the reſt of <hi>Lacedemon.</hi> For when
<hi>Hercules</hi> deceaſed, and changed this mortall for an immortall life
with the gods: his children in the begining by the power of the enemies
nouriſhed too and fro with many trauells: but after the death of
<hi>Euriſthus,</hi> they ſet vp their reſt amongſt the
<hi>Doreans;</hi> at laſt, three ages after they went to <hi>Delphos,</hi> to
conſult with the Oracle of certaine doubts: but the God <hi>Apollo</hi> gaue
them an anſwer to their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunds: and bad them returne into their owne
na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue and proper Country: conſidering therefore the oracle, they found
<hi>Argos</hi> to belong vnto them by right of propinquitie. For
<hi>Euriſtheus</hi> being dead, onely they of all the ſtocke of
<hi>Perſeus</hi> remained: <hi>Lacedemon</hi> being <pb facs="tcp:21613:7"/> brought
vnder ſeruitude, (for <hi>Tyndareus</hi> being driuen out of his Kingdome,)
after that <hi>Caſtor</hi> and <hi>Pollux</hi> vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed (from humane
ſocietie,) being reſtored to his Crowne by <hi>Hercules,</hi> gaue him this
Countrey both in recompence for his noble deeds, and for affinitie ſake with
his children, (<hi>Meſsena</hi> alſo then ſubdued by the ſword:) for
<hi>Hercules</hi> robbed of his cattle which he draue out of <hi>Erythia,</hi>
by <hi>Neleus</hi> and his children, (<hi>Neſtor</hi> onely excepted)
conquering that Cittie, put them to the ſword which offered him this wrong,
and made <hi>Neſtor</hi> Gouernour of this Cittie: iudging him a wiſe and
prudent man, in that he being the youngeſt, was not found culpable with his
other bretheren: conceiuing this therefore to be the meaning of the Oracle. And
taking in your Progenitours as confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates, and leuying a great Army, they
gaue in common this particular countrie to ſuch as followed them in the
warre; but tooke the maine Empire into their owne Soueraignitie, and vpon
theſe conditions interchang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably pledging their fidelitie, made an
inuaſion: But the danger and other Acts in this expedition, (not pertinent
for the preſent.) What neede I more amply perſecute: they being then
conquerours of the inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants in theſe foreſaid places, deuided the
Kingdome into three parts: yee therefore do abide euen to this day in the
league which yee made with our progeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours.</p>
            <p>Therefore in time paſt you haue beene more em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent then
others, and being ſo: ye may expect for the time to come, that your actions
ſhould make you more honourable then now yee are. But theſe of
<hi>Meſsena</hi> fell into that impietie, as they trecherouſly <pb facs="tcp:21613:7"/>
put to death this Citties founder, <hi>Creſphon</hi> the Lord of the
Countrie, one of <hi>Hercules</hi> Progenie, and their Commander. And his
ofſpring hauing eſcaped this danger, became ſuppliant to this Cittie,
iudging it worthie that ye by a due reuenge of this diſhonorable act to their
deceaſed father, ſhould get you honour ſurrendring vnto you this
Countrie; yee then ſuing vnto (god <hi>Apollo,</hi>) and he commanded to
vndertake this, and to redreſſe the wrong: ouercomming the
<hi>Meſsenians,</hi> thus haue poſſeſſed this Countrie. Nor haue I
accurately treated of what your right was from the beginning, for the preſent
time is not ſufficient to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>large all: but it was requiſite that I
ſhould diſcourſe of things more briefely then plainely.
Notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding I ſuppoſe euen by what hath been vttered, it will
appeare vnto all men why it ſhould be granted and confeſſed, that the
Countrie of right appertaineth to vs, we poſſeſſing it on no other
tearmes, rather then to be any way queſtioned or doubted of. For wee in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habit
this by donation from <hi>Hercules</hi> of-ſpring, and being warranted from
the Oracle of <hi>Apollo</hi> confirmed, and by conqueſt of them that
poſſeſſed it: that other we haue taken from the ſame men, in the
ſame manner, and by the ſame Oracle. And if it be ſo with vs, that there
can be no proud command layd on vs touching contradiction in the one, or the
relinquiſhing of <hi>Spar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta,</hi> it is a needleſſe labour to trouble
our braines con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning <hi>Meſsena.</hi> And if none of you thinke it fit
that you ſhould liue baniſhed from your owne countrie: yee ought alſo to
be like minded concerning <hi>Meſſena.</hi> For we muſt pleade the ſame
right and reaſon touching them both. Nor is this vnknowne to you, that all 
<pb facs="tcp:21613:8"/> men account poſſeſſion whether priuate or publike, by
preſcription of time, to be proper and patrimoniall. Now wee got
<hi>Meſſena</hi> before the <hi>Perſians</hi> got their Monarchie, or
ſubdued the continent <hi>(Aſia,)</hi> and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſome Citties of
<hi>Greece</hi> were made habitable. Theſe things remaining thus to you, they
(the <hi>Thebanes</hi>) haue yeelded <hi>Aſia</hi> to a ſtranger as his own
patrimonie: who hath not had the Empire 200 yeares, but would take away
<hi>Meſſena</hi> from vs, who haue poſſeſſd it more then double
that time. And <hi>Palatiua</hi> and <hi>Theſpeas</hi> they haue now a late
dimoliſhed: but <hi>Meſſena</hi> after 300 yeares ſpace they would haue
reaedified, in both brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the conditions and league. And as they ſhould
as of right reduce <hi>Meſſena,</hi> yet they ſhould be iniuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous or
offend vs with more colour, or ſhew of reaſon. But now they plant
vaſſells vpon our confines; ſo this is not the moſt fearefull offence,
that we ſhould looſe our Cittie contrarie to all right, but to behold our
vaſſells to be now our Citties Maſters.</p>
            <p>Out of that which followeth ye ſhall euidently diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne, that
now we ſuffer intollerable wrong, and that formerly we iuſtly held
<hi>Meſsena;</hi> for after many perills were ſuſtained by vs, we were
conſtrained to make peace, fearing much worſe then if we had bin enemies:
but yet our couenants being drawne in thoſe times, wherein it was not
poſſible to haue better, there fell out ſome contention about other
things: but about <hi>Meſſena,</hi> neither the great King (of
<hi>Perſia,</hi>) nor the State of the <hi>Thebanes</hi> at any time could
obiect any thing for the holding thereof.</p>
            <p>And how ſhall we find a more elaborate teſtimonie touching our
right, then this decree make knowne by <pb facs="tcp:21613:8"/> our enemyes, and notified
in our greareſt infortunats. Moreover the oracle which all acknowledg to be
moſt ancient, uniuerſall, and faithfull, foreknew that then
<hi>Meſſena</hi> was ours, when vppon the guift or donation of
<hi>Creſphons</hi> princely heires, it bid vs receiue the Cittie, and releiue
the wronged; but the warres continuing a long time, both parties ſending to
<hi>Delphos,</hi> they ſeeking for ſuccour, and we queſtioning how we
might with moſt celeritie be poſſeſſed of the Cittie, the Oracle gaue
no anſwer at all vnto them, as making no iuſt pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition, but declared to vs
what ſacrifices we ſhould of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer, and from whom we ſhould haue moſt
ſtrong ayde. And how can any giue a more ſure and cleare teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny then
theſe? Firſt it was manifeſted, that we received this Countrie of the
true Lord, and owners thereof, (nor is it vnneceſſarie breifly to repeate
and inculcate theſe points:) next by conqueſt, as many other Citties in
thoſe times were erected, after that we caſt out thoſe impious wrongers
of <hi>Hercules</hi> children, who were iuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly expulſed all countries.</p>
            <p>Add hereunto our right of poſſeſſion by times
pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription, our enimyes approbation, and the goddeſſe determination,
every one of which is ſufficient to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw their words that dare accuſe
vs, either now for covetouſnes we conclude a peace, or formerly for am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition
of other mens eſtates, we waged warre againſt the <hi>Meſſenians.</hi>
And of the poſſeſſion of <hi>Meſsena</hi> haply the matter affordeth
more to be ſpoken, but I ſuppoſe what is already ſaid is
ſufficient.</p>
            <p>But they which aduiſe vs to make peace, affirme, that it
behoveth wiſe and prudent men, not to carrie one and the ſame minde, in
managing their affaires <pb facs="tcp:21613:9"/> when they are in proſperitie as in
adverſitie, but to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plie to the time, and to follow Fortune, not to beare
mindes greater then meanes, nor to ſeeke for iuſtice in thoſe ſtraites,
but for expediency; In other things I a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree with them, but how expediency is
to be prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red before iuſtice, no man of the deepeſt conſultation, can
perſwade me. For I perceiue that for iuſtice ſake, Lawes were enacted,
and in iuſtice vpright and good men much glory and reioyce, and for
iuſtice, Citties governed honeſtly, and honorably labour moſt
excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly. Yea and the warres in old times haue had a ſuccesfull end, not
according to force but faith: and the whole life of man periſheth through
wickednes, but is conſerued by vertue. Therefore they muſt not be weake, or
faint-harted, that try all dangers for iuſt cauſes, but much rather they
who iniures others con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tumeliouſly, and cannot beare proſperitie moderatly.
Next you muſt caſt your eye on this poynt, that all mens opinions are
agreed concerning the iuſtneſſe of the matter, but difference is only
about the expediency thereof. And of two goods propounded: whereof the one is
manifeſt, and the other vncertayne, how can you but doe abſurdly, if yee
ſhall refuſe that which is certaine and out of queſtion, and chuſe that
which is doubtfull. Your owne election being ſo diſtracted in it ſelfe,
for it is comprehended in your ſpeeches: that we ſhould looſe nothing of
our owne, nor involue the State with any diſgrace, and being expoſed vnto
dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers for a good cauſe to hope our battails ſhall haue more proſperous
ſucceſſe then our enimyes. And in all theſe our adviſes to looſe
<hi>Meſſena,</hi> yee ſhall wrong your ſelues herein, and peradventure
miſſe in expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>encie <pb facs="tcp:21613:9"/> iuſtice, and other things, which you
expect. For it is not aſſured, that if wee graunt our enimyes de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunds, we
ſhall haue a firme peace, and I thinke yee are not ignorant, that all men
vſe to diſcourſe of iuſtice or equitie to thoſe that are defendants;
but on thoſe which are ſomewhat more ready in yelding to the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunds of
their enimyes, worſer conditions are im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed then at the firſt were
intended, ſo as it falleth out, that they who are inclined to warre, ſettle
a better peace, then they who eaſily ſubmitt to any condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
            <p>And that I may not be thought to waſt more time about theſe
things leauing them all, I will addreſſe my ſpeach to the moſt
ſubſtantiall poynt. If never any, at any time having been put to the
worſe, haue reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered themſelues, nor overcome their enimyes, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
could we by any likelihood hope to be by warres advanced. But if oft times it
hath come to paſſe that the ſtronger haue been vanquiſhed by the
weaker, and they who haue laid ſeidge, haue been put to the worſt by
thoſe who haue ben beſeidged, what wonder were it, that the eſtate
wherein we now ſtand, ſhould admit alteration. But of our Cittie I can
averre no ſuch mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; for in former times none ever thought ſtronger then
wee, invaded theſe territories; but of others ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny inſtancies may be
vſed, and eſpecially of the Cittie of the <hi>Athenians,</hi> whom we
ſhall find by incroaching vpon others to be much blamed by the
<hi>Grecians.</hi> But for their revenging of wrong, haue ben prayſed of all
men. And if I ſhould recount the old peril<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s which the vnder went againſt the <hi>Amazones, Thracians,</hi>
and <hi>Peloponeſians,</hi> who breaking into theſe Countries with 
<pb facs="tcp:21613:10"/> 
               <hi>Euriſtieus,</hi> I ſhould be thought to tell you of
things too high, and remote from theſe preſent times: but in the
<hi>Perſian</hi> warre: who knoweth not out of how great calamitie, into how
great proſperitie they were ray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed; for they only out of the inhabitants,
which came from <hi>Peloponeſus,</hi> perceiuing the power of the Barbare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans
to be vnſubſiſtable, thought it vnworthy for them, to condeſend to the
conditions propounded to them: but preſently reſolved, to make leſſe
reckoning of their Citties ſubverſion, then to become ſervily in
ſubiecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Therefore, forſaking their Territories, and Cit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, (minding
their Countries fredome) aſſociating vs in their dangers, obtained ſuch a
change, that they, who for a few dayes were made a ſpoyle, were for a long
time after Lords over others; neyther in this Cit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie onely is it very
available for the common good, to take courage and to avenge our ſelues vpon
our eni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myes; but alſo even <hi>Dionyſius</hi> the Tyrant: by his exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
confirmeth the ſame. He being beſeidged by the <hi>Carthaginians</hi>
(there being left) and having no ſafegard or defence for him,) but hemmed in
with warre, and his ſubiects hatefully harted towards him, the tyrant offered
to eſcape by Sea-flight, one of his ſervants ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventured to ſay, he that
dyeth a King, leaues a faire Monument, whereupon, being aſhamed of what hee
had purpoſed, and againe beſtirring himſelfe and tak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing armes, ſlaying
many millions of the <hi>Carthaginians,</hi> made his Soveraignty over his
Subiects farre more firme, and that power which he firſt had being more
ſtrengthened, he ended his dayes in King-like autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, and left his
ſonne in the ſame honour, and princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pallitie, wherewith hee was
inveſted. In like ſort to <pb facs="tcp:21613:10"/> theſe, did <hi>Amyntas</hi> the
King of the <hi>Macedonians,</hi> for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ouerthrowne in fight by the
barbarous people, that bordered vpon him, and being ſtript of all
<hi>Mace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donia,</hi> firſt he minded to leaue his Countrie and to ſaue his
perſon, but hearing one commend that, which was ſpoken to
<hi>Dioniſius,</hi> and taking courage as he did, ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſed a ſmale
Caſtle, or hould, and ſending for aid thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, within three Monthes
ſpace, he regained all <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedonia,</hi> and raigning all the reſidue of
his life, dyed ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry aged; we ſhall be very weary both in hearing, and
ſpeaking, if we ſhould ſearch out all ſuch actions.</p>
            <p>If we ſhould remember the deedes concerning the <hi>Thebean</hi>
warre, we could not but lament for theſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent accidents; but for the
future wee conceiue better hope, for they being ſo hardy as to ſuſtaine
our aſſaults and threats, in this eſtate ſtood their affaires, that at
o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther times being in ſubiection to vs, now they ſeeke no leſſe then to
command vs, it is a ſenſles thing to thinke that when as ſuch alterations
haue ben in others, their ſhould be a ſtand in vs onely. But we muſt not
bee daunted with our preſent eſtate and beſtirr for the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and
truſt in what time muſt bring forth, being confident: that Citties remedy
ſuch calamities by wiſe Goverment at home, and by marſhall skill abroad.
Nor ſhall any dare to gaineſay, that our experience in the warres, is not
much more then others, and for good Domiſtick Govermentt, it is in vs alone:
ſuch as it ought to be; which being ſo, our affaires muſt needes be more
fortunate then theirs, who beſtow ſmall care vpon either of theſe
two.</p>
            <p>But ſome inveigh againſt the warre and tax it by vncertainty
of events, vſing as many other arguments, <pb facs="tcp:21613:11"/> ſo eſpecially
thoſe diſaſtars which haue befallen vs, and thinke it ſtrange that any
ſhould iudge it fitt, to put confidence in a thing ſo hazardous, and
difficult. But I haue knowne much happineſſe to haue accrewed to many by
the warres, and through peace many haue loſt. For none of theſe courſes
are of themſelues: ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ill, or good. But as a man ſhall vſe things,
and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunities, ſo of neceſſity haue they their events. For it is
behouefull that they who are in proſperitie, ſhould deſire peace, for
ſo in that eſtate they ſhall greatly pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue that they haue. But
thoſe that are in adverſitie muſt liſten vnto warre. For by troubles
and buſtling, a ſpeedie mutation will follow, and I doubt we practiſe the
cleane contrary to this.</p>
            <p>For when we might haue liued at eaſe and pleaſure, we followed
warre more then was expedient: but now that we are driven into great
diſtreſſes, wee ſeeke for eaſe, and take counſell for ſecuritie.
But they who would inioy their liberty, muſt ſhun compoſitions ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred
by commaund or ſtrong hand: as tending vnto ſervitude. And ſhould come to
parleyes, either when they haue ſuper eminency, the better of their enimyes
or at leaſt equall to them,<note place="margin">aliter) the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of
peace which any pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like ſtate ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines of the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimy are ſuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the
terms wherein their warre hath en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded.</note> that they all may haue ſuch a
League, as may bring a totall ceſſation of armes; which yee minding, ought
not raſhly to caſt your ſelues into baſe and ignominious co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ditions of
peace, nor appeare more timorous adviſers in your Countries behalfe, then in
other affaires, and remember that in times paſt, if but onely one
<hi>Lacedemonian</hi> did ayde any of their confederate Citties, which was
beſeidged, all men would confeſſe, that for that one man only, they did
obtaine their ſafety. And a man may heare of our aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtours <pb facs="tcp:21613:11"/>
many ſuch men, and my ſelfe can reckon ſome of moſt note, and name.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Paidaretus</hi> going to <hi>Chius</hi> with his navie:
preſerved that Cittie. <hi>Braſidas</hi> entring <hi>Amphipolis</hi>
marſhalling but a few of them that were beſeiged, in fight over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>threw many
of the beſeidgers. <hi>Gylippus</hi> alſo ayding the <hi>Syracuſians</hi>
did not onely ſaue them, but captived all their enimyes army royall, both by
Sea, and Land. And how can this but be dishonourable to you, that in thoſe
times every one of you, was enough to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue other Citties, but now all of
you dare not at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt to ſaue your owne. And you haue filled all
<hi>Aſia</hi> and Europe with your tryumphes: when you fought for others, yet
for your owne Country, ſo manifeſtly not only wronged, but reproached,
there is no appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of any battell, which you haue fought worthy ſo much
as to be named, but other Citties in the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of our Empire, haue endured
the moſt extreame Leaguers, but we our ſelues haue not the courage to beare
the leaſt hardſhippe, that we be not compelled to doe that which is
dishonorable.</p>
            <p>Now when as we are furniſhed with good troopes of horſe well
fedd and trained for the warres, ſhould we now make ſo baſe a peace? As
may be ſeeme only thoſe that are brought downe to the loweſt ebb of
ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſities, and want meanes for their dayly ſuſtentation.</p>
            <p>But this of all is moſt vnworthy: if we who are thought the
moſt actiue of all the <hi>Graecians,</hi> ſhall be moſt ſlow in
theſe deliberations. And is it meete to mention ſome of theſe braggs,
with which we are out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faced by theſe men? They (ſay theſe men) who are
but once overcome, and haue but one aſſault, or im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion 
<pb facs="tcp:21613:12"/> made on them, ſo effeminately yeelding, to what conditions
ſoever the enimyes propound, how will they be able to endure a continuall
calamitie? And who would not diſdaine vs, (the <hi>Meſſenians</hi>
indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the ſeige of twentie yeares in this Country,) if we ſhould
through a ſodaine compoſition forſake the ſame, not remembring our
Aunceſtours, but what they with much labour, and danger, haue
poſſeſſed, wee ſhould through a verball perſwaſion caſt away?
Which ſome nothing reſpecting, nor regarding the dishonour that will fall
vpon vs, adviſe thoſe things: which will make our State for ever infamous.
And ſo eagerly doe they exhort vs to deliver vp <hi>Meſsena;</hi> that they
haue been bold to diſcover the weaknes of our Cittie, and the ſtrength of
the enemy, and bid them which oppoſe their adviſe, to anſwer and tell
from whence any help can be expected, wherevpon we ſhould giue counſell for
a warre.</p>
            <p>Truely I thinke the beſt procuring of ayd for warr, and the
moſt aſſured, is to vndertake iuſt cauſes. For it is right and meet,
that even the good pleaſure of the gods ſhould aſſiſt ſuch; if we
may coniecture of the future by the preſent. Add herevnto to governe the
Common wealth well, and warily, and even vnto the death to reſiſt the
enimy, and to iudge nothing ſo heavie, as to be ill ſpoken of by our owne
Countrie men, which worthy diſpoſition is to be found more in our Nation,
then in any other: And truely for my parr, I had rather go to the warres
aſſiſted with troupes of our owne Nation, then with the ſtrength of
many millions of other Nations.</p>
            <p>For we know our predeceſſours comming into theſe 
<pb facs="tcp:21613:12"/> Countries, were not Conquerours by the multitude of others aydes,
but by thoſe virtues before recited. Therefore it is unworthy to feare the
enimy, becauſe they are many, but rather herein to ſet vp our
reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſith we ſee our ſelues ſo to haue ſuffered calamities,
as none others ever did, continuing in thoſe conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions (of our
Aunceſtours) which were ordained from the beginning: But ſome not
contenting, nor contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning themſelues within their happy eſtates, but
being of turbulent ſpirits, others combined with warlike confederacies
invading other Citties: others doyng the cleane contrary; and the reſt are at
difference with their neighbours, rather about the boundes of their
territories, then warring againſt vs. So as I wonder men ſhould ſeeke
greater helpes in warre, then thoſe which the weakeneſſes of the enimyes
afford, theſe ſhalbe our aydes, and aſſiſtance.</p>
            <p>But if it be needfull to ſpeake of forraine aide, there be many
I thinke that would leavie forces for vs. Firſt I know the
<hi>Athenians,</hi> though they ſtand not for vs in all things, yet for their
owne ſafetie will doe any thing: and ſome other States will ioyne it in
Counſell, for what may as well now availe vs, as themſelues. Yea,
<hi>Dionyſius</hi> the tyrant, and the King of <hi>Aegipt,</hi> and other
Potentates of <hi>Aſia</hi> as in them is, will readily ſend vs
aſſiſtance. And beſides theſe the wealthy and famous
<hi>Graecians</hi> endevours in all excellent actions, though yet not ioyned to
vs, yet in good will are with vs, of whom we haue good cauſe to hope well for
the future. And I thinke the people in <hi>Peloponeſus</hi> and that Popu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar
State which we may well thinke, although not hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto yet at this time would
take care on our ſide. <pb facs="tcp:21613:13"/> For they haue not obtained by their
falling from vs what they expected: but inſtead of their libertie the
contrary hath befallen them: For they haue both loſt the beſt men in their
eſtate, and are now becom ſubiect to the worſt of their owne Cittizens:
and when they would liue after their owne lawes, they are fallen into many and
greivious breaches of all Lawe. And where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as heretofore they were wont with vs:
to goe againſt others, now they ſee others warring againſt them, and the
ſeditions which they heard before amongſt their neighbours, now they alſo
behould almoſt every day, commotions amongſt themſelues. And they are
ſo brought vnder by afflictions as they be now, not who are the moſt
miſerable among them, for none of their Citties are ſo without dangers of
ſword, that hath not their neighbours doing them miſcheife, ſo as their
territories are layd waſt, their Citties dimoliſhed, their dwelling
houſes ruinated, their goverment tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned top-ſide turvie, their lawes
abrogated, which while they enioyed: they were the moſt happie of all the
<hi>Graecians;</hi> and ſo faithleſſe, and hoſtile are they among
themſelues, as they rather feare their owne Cittizens, then the enimy. And
in-ſtead of that wealth which they enioyned vnder vs, and good will which
they had from vs, they are fallen into ſuch barbaroneſſe and
hard-hartineſſe, as they, that haue wealth, more contentedly will caſt it
into the ſea, then to impart it to the poore in neceſſitie, and the poore
had rather rob, and forcibly catch from the rich, then take them vp though they
might find them by chaunce. And abrogating their ſacrifices, they
ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice one another on their altars; and there are more <pb facs="tcp:21613:13"/>
exils now out of one Citty, then there were before out fo all
<hi>Peloponeſus,</hi> notwithſtanding all which recited miſeries, thoſe
which are concealed are more then are declared, there is no wretchednes, nor
heauines which concurreth not with the times, with which ſome are already,
and others very ſhortly will be filled: all ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king to find deliuerance
from the preſent calamitie. For think not things can continue in this ſtay,
for they whom proſperities hath burthened, how can they long indure the
waight of aduerſitie? therefore not onely if wee get the victorie by fight,
but alſo if wee remaine inioying peace yee ſhall ſee them changed, and
they will thinke that confederation with vs will bee their beſt ſafeties:
this therefore is the hope I haue,</p>
            <p>And I ſo farre abſtaine from yeelding to our ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies demands,
that if none of theſe things come to paſſe, no aide from others, and
though ſome of the <hi>Graecians</hi> ſhould hurt vs, and others of them
ſhould neglect vs, I would not hereafter be otherwiſe minded, but would
ſuſtaine any dangers of warre rather then ſigne any ſuch conditions:
for I ſhould be much aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of both theſe, either to condemne our
Anceſtors, as if they had iniuriouſly taken from the
<hi>Meſſenians</hi> their territories: or that wee, if they haue lawfully
poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed them, ſhould giue away any part, beyond right and equitie.
And neither of theſe two muſt be done; but wee muſt conſider how wee
may make a warre be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeming our worth, leaſt wee ſhould giue the lye vpon
them, who praiſe and admire our ſtate: but rather ſo to behaue our
ſelues, that they might be thought to haue praiſed vs leſſe then wee
haue merited. For I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe nothing more grieuous ſhall euer fall out
then <pb facs="tcp:21613:14"/> what now is; and that our enemies conſultations and
actions ſhall much aduantage vs. But if our hope ſhould be fruſtrate, and
wee ſhould on all partes bee circumuented, and that wee could not preſerue
the State, theſe are dangerous things which I ſhall ſpeake of, (yet I
will not ſpare to ſpeake freely of them, for theſe are better and more
agreeable to our wiſdomes to be told among the <hi>Graecians</hi> then
thoſe which ſome ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſe vnto) I hold it meete our parents, children, and
wiues, and other our people ſhould bee ſent ſome into <hi>Sicilia,</hi>
and <hi>Italy,</hi> ſome into <hi>Syrene,</hi> ſome into <hi>Epirus,</hi>
whom all theſe will willingly receiue with ſufficient proportion of ground
for their habitation, and other prouiſion for liuelihood, ſome in rendring
thankes for the benifits already receiued from vs, others in expec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of
the profit they may receiue for the good they doe to vs. Thoſe which remaine
and are willing, and able to vndergoe perills ſhall forſake the Cittie, and
all their poſſeſſions, and goods ſauing what we can carrie with vs,
taking ſome Caſtle or Hold which is well fortified, or fitteſt for warre,
to offend and infeſt our enemies on all ſides both by ſea and land, till
they ſhall giue ouer challenging that which is ours. And if wee ſhall
valorouſly attempt theſe things without delay, wee ſhall ſee thoſe
that now Lord it ouer vs, and giue the Lawe, become our humble ſuppliants and
ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters to receiue <hi>Meſsena</hi> againe, and to make peace with them.
Now which of the Citties in <hi>Peloponeſus</hi> hath vndertaken ſo great a
warre as is requeſite this ſhould be; if your wills be not wanting. Yea who
will not be aſtoniſhed, and tremble, at an army ſo mightilie com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacted,
and ſo well exerciſed, ſo iuſtly incenſed againſt <pb facs="tcp:21613:14"/>
thoſe who haue beene the cauſes of theſe miſchiefes, ſo reſolute to
ſpend their liues in publicke ſeruice to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply them ſelues vpon nothing
elſe but vpon the warres, neglecting all other occaſions not vnlike thoſe
armies which conſiſt of mercinary forces whoſe trade is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but
warre.<note place="margin">A diſcription of Mansfieds Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my.</note> Moreouer
hauing no certaine Cittie of abode, able to liue without houſes in the open
field, rouing vp and downe throughout all countries, and can make them ſelues
borderers, or neighbours on whom ſoeuer they will, and thinke all places
which are fit for warre to bee their habitation and natiue Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie.</p>
            <p>I thinke if theſe wordes allready ſpoken by me were diuulged
through out <hi>Graece,</hi> our enemies would find themſelues very much
perplexed, and ſo much the more if neceſſitie force vs to put this in
execution. For what ſhall we imagine they will thinke, that they ſhould be
ſubiect to ſuffer miſcheife, but ſhall not be able to doe vs any hurt,
and ſhall behould ſeige layd to their Citties, but ours ſo well appoynted
that it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not fall into the like affliction, beſide nouriſhment for our
bodyes ſhalbe eaſily had out of our goods brought with vs, together with
ſuch as ſhall come by forraging and ſpoyle, but theirs will be hard to
come by, becauſe it is not all one, to provide for an armie and to feed a
company of people in a Cittie, and that would vex them moſt of all, when they
ſhall heare, that our people doe floriſh in great experience, and wealth,
but ſhall ſee their owne every day hunger-ſtar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, and themſelues not
able to ſupply their indigen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, yea, when they ſhall plough their ground:
they ſhall haue theirs reaped for them againſt their wills, <pb facs="tcp:21613:15"/>
and on the other ſide if they leaue it vntilled, they ſhall neuer haue to
ſuffice them.</p>
            <p>But perhaps they will vnite their forces and raiſe a generall
army, and follow vs at the heeles, and ſo hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der vs from hurting them. But
what will be more wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed of vs, then to meet their fulleſt forces, and
their beſt preparations to battail, and in the ſame difficulties with vs
pitching their Tents againſt vs: their ſouldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers ill ordered, out of the
common rout, vſing many generalls, but we ſhall eaſily make a quicke hand
of them, by compelling them to fight at our pleaſure not at their owne
choice.</p>
            <p>The reſidue of the day would faile mee, if I ſhould take in
hand to tell how much our eſtate would be bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered by theſe courſes.
This is againe manifeſt, that we excell not the other <hi>Graecians</hi> in
greatnes of our Cittie, nor in multitude of men, but becauſe we haue framed
our gouernment, like to an Army well ordred, willing to obay the commanders.
And if wee ſhall repreſent that whoſe imitation hath profitted vs, it is
not ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure that wee ſhall be more powerfull then our ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, for wee
know that they who were made Lords of this Citty, hauing but a ſmall army
when they came into <hi>Peloponeſus,</hi> haue achieued many and mightie
en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpriſes.</p>
            <p>It ſhall therefore well become vs to imitate our an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtors,
and returning to our firſt originall becauſe we haue ſtept aſide,
endeuour to recouer our auncient ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, but wee ſhall doe moſt
diſgracefully if knowing how the <hi>Athenians</hi> left their Countrey for
the ſafegard of other <hi>Graecian,</hi> we ſhould not dare to leaue our
Cit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie for the ſafety of our ſelues. And that when wee <pb facs="tcp:21613:15"/> ought
to giue examples to others of ſuch worthy at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiuements, wee are not willing
ſo much as to imitate their honourable actions. Yea this is much more
re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diculous, if the <hi>Phoceans</hi> flying from the dominion of a great King,
leauing <hi>Aſia,</hi> fled into <hi>Maſſalia,</hi> wee ſhould come to
this puſillanimitie, as to ſuffer, or vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dergoe their imperiouſnes, of
thoſe whoſe maſters we haue been heretofore. We muſt not ere in our
minds to reuolue that day in which wee ſhould ſeperate our moſt deare,
and neere ſuddainly from vs. But rather are wee to looke backe to thoſe
times in which as vic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours ouer our enemies wee ſhall rectifie our Cittie,
and imbrace thoſe which are ſoe neere and deare vnto vs. And now wee are to
make it appeare to all, that we haue been without deſert infortunate, and
that in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer times wee iuſtly would haue commanded ouer o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. And thus
ſtands the matter. I haue made this ſpeech, not as that we ſhould
inſtantly do theſe things, nor as though our ſafety conſiſted in no
other courſe, but as deſirous to vndergoe theſe, and farre greater
mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries, before wee make compoſition about <hi>Meſſena,</hi> ſuch
as they require. Nor would I ſo feruently ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hort you to warre, if I found
not that this courſe which I haue propounded to be the beſt way for a faire
and firme peace for future, but out of that which others haue counſelled
vnto, it will be diſhonorable, and for no time durable. For if wee ſhall
dwell neere this Cit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie enlarged and repaired, who diſcerneth not, that we
ſhall euer be ending of our daies in tumults, and dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers? Theſe therefore
diſcourſing of ſecuritie, hide from themſelues that they make but a few
dayes peace for vs, which will beget hereafter a continuall warre,</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:21613:16"/>Faine would I heare of them, for what things and when
they thinke we ſhould fight euen to death, Not then when our enemies impoſe
vnreaſonable conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons vpon vs? Not then when they would catch vs out of
our countrie, and make free our bond-ſlaues, and place them in the countrie
which our Anceſtours left to vs? Not then when they not onely turne vs out of
that wee haue, but make vs the reproach and ſcorne of our neighbours. I
truely thinke that for theſe it is fit to endure not onely fight, bvt flight,
and death. For it is farre better to end our liues in the honour which wee
haue, then to prolong our dayes in dishonour, ſubiecting our ſelues to our
enimyes commaund.</p>
            <p>If I muſt not diſſemble to ſay what is evident. It will be
more tollerable that our enimyes ſhould de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy vs, then deride vs. For
they who haue lived in ſuch reputation of courage and worth as wee haue done:
muſt chooſe one of theſe two, either to be emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent among the
<hi>Graecians,</hi> or elſe to dye every mothers child of vs, without
ſubiecting our ſelues to baſſenes, which we muſt thinke on, not with
loue to our liues, nor following the opinion of our confederates, whoſe
guids, and rulers we haue ben thought worthy to be heeretofore. But theſe
things being conſidered, to chooſe not what is moſt expedient for them,
but what is moſt comely for <hi>Lacedemon,</hi> and for our braue acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.
For of the ſame things all muſt not ever delibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate alike, but as from the
beginning every one hath layd the foundation of that matter. For none will
im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute it as a fault to the <hi>Epidareans, Philaſians,</hi> and
<hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinthians,</hi> if they regarded nothing but the life, and the
preſervation of themſelues; but it is not decent, <pb facs="tcp:21613:16"/> for the
<hi>Lacedemonians</hi> to ſtoope to all kind of meanes, but if they cannot
ſaue their liues with their honour, death muſt be preferred. For they who
contend a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout vertue, muſt labour in nothing ſo much as that they may be
ſeene to doe no ſhamefull act. And the cowardice of Citties is no leſſe
perceiued in ſuch de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terminations, then in the hazards and perrills of the
warre. For the greateſt part of the things their done conſiſteth in
Fortune, but what is decreed in thoſe things: is the very index of
vnderſtanding. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we muſt alike ſtudeouſly prouide for thoſe
things which are heere decreed, as the things which in the warres are fought
for. And I wonder that they who would dye for their proper eſtate, ſhould
not beare the ſame minde for the publique, for which wee ſhould ſuffer
any thing, and not ſhame our Cittie, or ſee it forſake the Orders, and
gouerments where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in our Anceſtors eſtabliſhed it. And of theſe many
affaires, and mightie dangers which preſſe vs, and muſt be avoyded of vs,
this muſt eſpecially be looked vnto, that we appeare not to doe ought
effeminately, nor yeeld to our enemyes beyond what is right. For it is a
ſhame that they who are dignified to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand the <hi>Graecians,</hi>
ſhould ſtoope to their enimyes demaunds, and be ſo farre caſt behind
their Aunce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtours, that whereas they to get Soueraigntie ouer others, were
ready to ſuffer death. One the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, we doe vndertake the danger of a
warre, to ridd our ſelues from ſubiection vnto others.</p>
            <p>Well may wee be aſhamed to looke on the games of
<hi>Olympus</hi> and other famous ſolemnities, wherein euery one of vs was
emulous, and more admirable <pb facs="tcp:21613:17"/> then any champion that did beare away
the bell in theſe games. Into which, how thinke you any of vs dare enter:
when we are like to be ſcorned, inſtead of being honoured, inſtead of
being conſpicuous aboue all for vertue, and hereafter obſcured and
deſpiſed of them for our daſtardlineſſe.</p>
            <p>Beſides we ſhall ſee our vaſſalls out of that Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey
which our Aunceſtours left vs, bring greater of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings and ſacrifices then
we: and we ſhall heare from them reproaches ſo diſdainefull as may be
ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected. For thoſe who were before our ſeruants, and now haue pircked vp:
to ſtand one euen ground to make conditions with vs being their Maſters:
with which Couenanrs they will ſo pinche vs, as no man living by words can
expreſſe; whereof we muſt (now) conſider, and not then repine when
their is no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther remedie. And now let vs be watchfull how none of thoſe
things may happen, or light on vs.</p>
            <p>For what ſhamefull baſenes is this, in former times we could
not endure to be equalized of free men, but now we ſhall be ſeene to
ſuffer the bold inſolencies of bondmen. And wee ſhall be thought
heretofore to haue flouriſhed in brauadoes, and when we were encouraged no
better then other men, yet to haue ſet a good face vpon it and to haue put on
a fayned grauitie.</p>
            <p>Let vs therefore giue no cauſe to ſuch, as vſe to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vile
vs, and endeauour to conuince their euill ſpeeches with our deedes, acted in
imitations of our Aunce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors worthy exploits. Remember our predeceſſours
warring againſt the <hi>Arcadians,</hi> whom as they ſay ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, or
ordered vnder the buckler of a few targette<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers, <pb facs="tcp:21613:17"/> got the victory
of many millions. And alſo thoſe three hundred, who at <hi>Thyrea,</hi>
vanquiſhed all the <hi>Arguies.</hi> And thoſe embattailed thouſand at
<hi>Thermopolis,</hi> who fighting with Seventie millions of the
<hi>Barbarians,</hi> turned not their backes neither were ſubdued, but left
their liues vpon life, where they were ſet in aray, ſhewing themſelues
ſuch, as they who imploy their beſt art and skill in celebrating
commendations, cannot paralell their prayſes with their vertues.</p>
            <p>Calling all theſe therefore to mind, let vs cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragiouſly
prepare to battel, not expecting any others to ſalue our preſent maladie,
but what dangers doe aſſaile vs, let vs aſſay to defeate. For it
behoueth men of valour in ſuch times to be more couragious: For proſperitie
couereth the vices, and cowardice of all men, but aduerſitie diſcouereth
what all men are, wherein we muſt ſhew that we haue been better trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned,
and inſtructed in vertue. Nor muſt we deſpaire, out of thoſe things
which we now haue: ſhould ariſe thoſe things which we yet ioy not.</p>
            <p>For I ſuppoſe yee are not ignorant that many acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons haue
happened: which at the firſt all men ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted miſeries, and were greiued
with the indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring thereof, but afterward yee experimented the ſelfe ſame
to be the cauſes of much happines. And what need we forraine examples? (I
ſay) of the <hi>Athentans,</hi> and <hi>Thebans,</hi> haue not come to that
greatnes by peace, but out of calamities of warres haue recouered
them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues: and of one is become the chiefe of all, and the other at this
inſtant, ſo great, as none would euer haue ſuppoſed it could euer haue
been for renowne, <pb facs="tcp:21613:18"/> and ſhining greatnes, affect not to be
produced out of ſloth, but out of bloody conflicts, in deſire wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of,
neither our bodyes, nor liues, nor ought elſe that we haue, are to be
ſpared. For we ſhall ſet all things in good plight, and recouer our State
into that digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, from whence it is lapſed, we ſhall ſurpaſſe all
our Anceſtors in honour, and ſhall leaue nothing for our ſucceſſours
to exceede vs; and we ſhall be in ſo good caſe that they would ſpeake
well, who are willing to ſpeake well of vs, ſhall not be able by their
praiſes to equall our exploits.</p>
            <p>Neither muſt we forget this, that all men ſet their minds and
hopes on this Parliament, and open your determinations in it. So therefore let
euery man ſet downe his reſolution, as if wee were now vpon the common
ſtage of all Greece. It is but one marke that we ayme at in all theſe
deliberations. For if we will reſolue to maintaine our vpon equall tearmes
euen vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till death, we ſhall not only be well reported of, but all the
reſidue of our time we ſhall liue ſecured. But if we be faint-hearted in
perils, we ſhall perplex our ſelues with many incumbrances. Therefore
exhorting one another, let vs pay backe to our countrey her due for breeding
and feeding vs; and let vs not behold our Lacedemon as it is now
contumeliouſly oppreſſed, and contemned. Neither let vs fruſtrate of
their hopes, ſuch as are our well wiſhers, nor making too much ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of
our liues, appeare traytors to our reputation, conſidering that it is the
higheſt point of honour to exchange a mortall bodie for an immortall Glory.
And (with expence of our liues, which we can enioy but for a few yeares, to
purchaſe that good name, <pb facs="tcp:21613:18"/> which we ſhall leaue to all our
poſteritie for euer. For it is much better by this exchange, to get that
honour which ſhall neuer weare out, then to hedge our ſelues in with great
reproaches for a little ſeaſon. And I thinke yee may be more encouraged to
warre, if yee repreſent vnto your minde, as preſent your parents, and your
children, theſe calling vpon you not to ſtaine the name of Sparta, nor the
lawes in which you were brought vp and inſtructed, nor the battels waged in
their dayes, theſe other challenging at your hands that countrey, which their
Anceſtors bequeathed them, their Soueraigntie ouer the Grecians, and their
princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>palitie which they receiued from their forefathers to whom we cannot
anſwer, that either of them make vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſt requeſts. I know not why I
ſhould prolong my ſpeech, only thus much: that if for the many warres in
this State, and dangers vndergone, our enemies at no time erected any trophe
againſt vs, while any King of our owne family was commander. And it is the
part of wiſe men that whom they haue vſed as Lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, and Generals in
Warre with victorious ſucceſſe, by theſe deliberately aduiſing
touching future dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, rather then by any others ſhould they be
per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
